[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software SE radio has an opening for a
volunteer host to produce five episodes
per year to apply please follow the
instructions on our website at se-
radio.net Conta
welcome to software engineering radio
this is Philip Winston my guest today is
Katherine Nelson Katherine is a
freelance data scientist and the author
of two O'Reilly books this year is
software engineering for data scientists
and her 2020 book building machine
learning pipelines co-authored with
Hannah hapka previously she was a
principal data scientist at sap Concur
and before that she had a career as a
geophysicist Katherine has a PHD in
geophysics from Durham University and a
master's of Earth Sciences from Oxford
University she is currently Consulting
for startups in the generative AI space
welcome Katherine thanks philli it's
great to be on the podcast today we're
going to discuss the role of the data
scientist and how this role can overlap
with or intersect software engineering
let's start with what is a data
scientist that's such a great question
because what a data scientist is depends
on where you work at some companies it
can be more in the data analytics space
and at others it can mean that you're
spending all your time training machine
learning models but overall I'd say
being a data scientist involves
translating business problems into data
problems solving them where possible and
then sometimes building machine learning
powered features so what skills does a
data scientist need either prior to
getting the role or what skills do they
need to develop to be good at the role
they need to have skills for working
with data so those would include a
knowledge of Statistics a knowledge of
coding to be able to manipulate the data
take courses in basic machine learning
learn about the algorithms that make up
machine learning data
visualization sometimes storytelling
with data how to weave those data
visualizations together to a coherent
whole a lot of data scientists will take
courses on data ethics data privacy
because sometimes that is part of the
data scientist's job as well it's a real
mixed bag it seems like data scientists
need perhaps more domain knowledge or
business knowledge than some engineering
roles why do you think this is I'd say
that's right I think it's because you're
translating the problems from a business
problem to a data problem so you might
be tasked to answer a problem such as
why are our customers churning why does
some customers leave the business and
you dig into the data to try and see
what features of a company are
correlated with them stopping using your
products so it might be something like
the size of the business or they might
have left given you feedback that has
some reasons for that so you can't
really answer a problem like that
without having a good sense of what the
business does what products there are
how things fit together so yeah I think
it involves a lot more context on a
typical project who does the data
scientist have to communicate with
typically the interesting thing I've
found with my data science career is I
wouldn't say I have a typical project so
I've done some projects where it's been
extremely expl
it's been like we might be considering
creating a new feature for the product
is this even possible it's really blue
sky and then there's other projects I've
worked on where it's been towards the
production end of things deploying new
models into production so I'm going to
be working with different people
depending on the type of project but
some commonalities would be a product
organization and obviously Engineers if
it's involving building features for
most of the episode we're going to be
talking about machine learning and AI
but as I understand it there's more to
data science than just these two Fields
can you give me example of a problem you
solved or a solution you came up with in
data science that didn't involve ml or
AI actually the example that I just
mentioned looking at why customers might
leave a business that involved no
machine learning at all it was a
predictive modeling problem but I didn't
use a machine learning solution so the
projects that are more around answering
questions versus building features are
the ones where there's a lower level of
machine learning AI usage and more
statistics or data visualization or
general data analysis skills I want to
mention two past episodes related to
data science there's episode 315 year on
jansen's on tools for data science that
was in 2018 and episode 286 Katie Malone
intro to machine learning 2017 Katie
milone is a data scientist so now let's
move into talking about machine learning
and AI to start with what is the
difference between these two fields and
in my research I think I've seen the
term AI has been evolving a lot so I'm
wondering what definitions you use the
most useful definition I've heard than
the one that I've adopted did and
continue to use was from a podcast that
I heard with Christopher Manning who's a
professor at Stanford University in
their natural language processing and
that is that if you're dealing with
machine learning then you're training a
model for one particular problem one
particular use but an AI model can
answer many problems so you might use
your AI model to power a chatbot but you
could use the same model to summarize
some text or extract some information
for some text whereas In classical
traditional machine learning if you
wanted to have a model that extracted
some information from some text you go
and collect a data set designed for
exactly that problem you take some of
the input text and what the output that
you wanted it to produce and then you
train your model and measure how
accurate it was on that particular
problem I'd like to talk a little bit
about the use of notebooks like Google's
collab in data science this is a
technique or a method that I think is
more common in data science than in
software engineering at large so I'm
wondering what are the pros and if there
are any cons of doing your work inside
of a notebook definitely I'm a huge fan
of Jupiter notebooks I love being able
to get the instant feedback on what my
code is doing which is particularly
useful when I'm looking at data all the
time I can print that data I can plot a
small graph of that data I can really
interact with that data while I'm coding
I find them incredibly useful when I'm
starting a project I don't quite know
where things are going I'm really
exploring around and trying to see what
the data I'm working with can do for me
or I'm starting with
basic machine learning model and seeing
if it learns anything about the problem
that I'm working on what sorts of signs
are there that maybe you need to switch
to just a traditional git repository
what starts to become difficult with a
notebook for me I refactor when I'm at
the point where I want to train that
model repeatedly so in a machine
learning problem I have chosen the
features that I want to work with I've
chosen the data that I want to work with
I've trained an initial model it's
getting a reasonable result but then I
want to train it
repeatedly and optimize the hyper
parameters and then eventually move
towards deploying it into production so
I think that's the main difference is
that when I just have code that I may
only run once I don't know where I'm
going I don't know exactly what the
final code base will look like that's
when I'm happiest in a Jupiter notebook
but when it's going to be run repeatedly
when I need to write tests when I need
to make sure that code is robust that's
when I do that refactor in a little
while we're going to talk through the
steps in a machine learning workflow
focusing on what it would be like to
make a automated reusable pipeline out
of them but let's talk a little bit more
about roles so I think you mentioned
data analyst relative to data scientists
let's talk about a machine learning
engineer that certainly comes up what is
your feeling about their role and how it
differs from either data science or
software engineer at many companies I
think it's the data scientists that will
make some initial Explorations and take
a fresh problem and say like is this
even a problem that we should be solving
with machine learning what type of
algorithms are suitable for this
particular problem train an initial
model prove that that model is going to
answer the question that's under
consideration and then it's the machine
learning engineer that takes over when
that has been established when those
initial experiments have been done and
then puts that model into production and
then they look more on the side of
monitoring that model check checking
that it's performance checking that it
returns its the inference happens in the
right amount of time and so on how about
at a smaller company I imagine that
people end up wearing multiple hats
until you're able to hire for all of
these different roles have you seen that
absolutely and sometimes at bigger
companies too if the data science team
is small then one person might wear a
lot of hats that's challenging because
it's a different mindset that you have
for when you're running an experiments
and being very like open to trying lots
of different things versus you want to
be in your production mindset where
everything has to run repeatedly where
it has to be very
robust let's specifically zoom in on the
relationship between data science and
software engineering what motivated you
to write your latest book software
engineering for data scientists a couple
of things really one is that it's a book
that I wanted to read earlier in my
career as a data scientist so a while
ago I joined a team where I was the only
data scientist on a team of developers
designers and so on and I found it hard
to just even understand the language
that the developers were using like many
data scientists my education didn't
include any kind of computer science
courses I didn't have that much
familiarity with software engineering
ways of working when I started as a data
scientist and I I had questions like
what is an API how do you build one and
I started getting interested in how I
could write better code and the books
that were available the examples were in
Java or they owned at web development
they weren't very accessible to me
writing code in Python and not needing
to have all the skills and background of
a web developer
and there's also data scientists have a
reputation for writing bad code and I
wanted to help change that I think you
answered this I was going to ask how
much software engineering training do
data scientists have and I think you're
saying that on the lower end it can be
more or less none I gu yeah there's a
couple of main routs for people getting
into data science one is from a hard
Science Background often physical
sciences or other science phds so they
have data analysis but they might be
writing more academic code that doesn't
need to be particularly robust doesn't
need to be particularly well tested and
another way is through data science
undergraduate degrees or Masters which
may include some level of programming
courses but there's so many things to
try and cover in a data science degree
that then it's hard to do that in depth
from your book can you pick just maybe
two two skills that you think would be
most beneficial for a data scientist to
learn one where I see there's often a
gap is in writing tests that's often
something that's not familiar to people
from a data science background and
that's because data science projects can
be so ad hoc so exploratory it's not
obvious when to add tests you can't add
tests to every single piece of code that
you're writing in the data science
project because half of the you're going
to throw away because you found that
that particular line of inquiry goes
nowhere there's not really a culture of
going back and adding those tests later
but if you then move on from that
exploratory code to putting your machine
learning model into production it's a
problem if your code's not tested
another one is that again it comes from
this exploratory nature often data
scientists are reluctant to use Version
Control when it's just an individual
project it seems like it's more hassle
than it's worth it's not obvious what
the benefits of that are until you start
working on a larger code base what
programming languages are commonly used
for data science I know python is common
to machine learning in general but there
are other more data science specific
languages I would say python is the
biggest data science language at this
point previously R was pretty big as
well but the proportion is declining a
bit but some people use Julia but it's
not received this widespread adoption
that python has those are the other two
I had down here R and Julia maybe
tackling the same question from a
different angle what should software
Engineers keep in mind about working
with data
scientists I think that data scientists
will be coming from a different mindset
than a software engineer so they used to
tackling very vague problems and turning
those into more data focused problems
and the thing with data science projects
is that you often don't know at the
start where you're going to end up if
you're working on a machine learning
problem you might find that the
algorithm that you end up using is very
simple or you might end up using
something that's very complex you might
start off with say it's a text Data
extraction problem you might start off
with trying a random Forest based
approach with some very simple text
features but that doesn't actually
perform very well the accuracy is low
then you might move on to trying a deep
learning model seeing if that works any
better so this makes it hard to estimate
at the start of the project how long
it's going to take or even what the
final outcome is going to be
is this going to be a large Model A 2
gab model where we're going to need some
specialized infrastructure to deploy it
or is it going to be very small and
it'll scale very easily so I think
keeping in mind that
uncertainty and it's not that the data
scientist is just bad at estimating that
is the nature of these projects it's not
clear what from the start what the end
is going to look like I could imagine a
scenario where the software Engineers
are eager to start deep into the
implementation phase but the data
scientist hasn't yet found the model for
sure and that might take some patience
and some time to iterate before it's
ready for exactly exactly yeah it's not
clear what that model is going to be
let's go through some typical machine
learning workflow steps and explain from
a data science point of view what are
some
considerations what's the procedure or
technique that might be used and if
we're working with software Engineers to
create an automated pipeline what are
some things to keep in mind about this
particular workflow step basically what
sorts of tools or techniques should we
keep in mind for each step so the first
one I have down is data ingest so I
guess there's a lot of different
projects but what are some things we
might be ingesting and what are we
feeding it into yeah this step is when
you take your data from wherever it's
stored in your company's infrastructure
and feeding it into the rest of the
pipeline this is the point where you
might also make the split into training
data and validation data and it's
picking up that data from whatever
format it's stored in and then
potentially transforming it into a
format that can move through the rest of
that pipeline can you give an example of
unstructured or structured data yeah
usually we call text or images
unstructured data and structured data is
data that's in a tabular format so that
the tabular data could be data about the
sizes of companies that you're
considering or the unstructured data
could be something like the text of a
complaints that you're trying to make a
prediction from so are there any
specific tools that might come into play
here whether they're Standalone tools or
libraries that are commonly used for
ingestion there's a few different
solutions for the entire pipeline that
have a data ingestion component
tensorflow extended is one of these
there's also Amazon Sage maker pipelines
and I believe mlflow has a similar
structure although I haven't worked with
that myself the next step I have is data
validation you talked about dividing the
data into training and validation sets
but that might be a different type of
validation yeah that's right so when
you're dividing your data into a
training and a validation set that's
used during the model training or
analysis model validation step to check
whether that model is sufficiently
accurate for the problem that you're
working on data validation is checking
that the data that you've ingested is
what you expect so some problems that
you might have with that data could
include there's the data's missing
something's gone wrong upstream and
suddenly you're getting null values in
your data and then your machine learning
model wouldn't be able to train with
those null values in there so the point
of the data validation step is that if
there's a problem with your data you can
stop the pipeline at this point rather
than go through the lengthy training
step only to find out that there's an
error at that point or your model isn't
as accurate as you've expected because
there's a quality issue with the data
let's pause for a second and talk about
when we would rerun the pipeline or why
we're rerunning the pipeline so if this
was just a oneoff exploratory
investigation and we created a model and
produced a visualization and that was
the end but in this case we're talking
about building a pipeline so when is it
that we rerun this pipeline is it
because we have new data is it because
we're trying to train a better model or
what situations and I guess related to
that is do we rerun the entire thing or
is it being able to rerun portions of so
for many business problems the data
doesn't stay static the data changes
through time people behave differently
with your product and so on so that
causes the model performance to degrade
with time because if you've trained um
model at a specific point in time it's
been trained on that data and then as
your usage pattern changes then that
model is not quite so relevant to that
data so the performance drops that's a
time when you might want to retrain that
model and usually you'd want to run the
entire training pipeline all the way
through if you just run part of it you
don't actually change anything because
the artifact that you get at the end of
the pipeline that you're going to deploy
into production is that trained model on
that updated data so as part of
validation how do you measure data
quality or under what situation would
the data fail validation that might be
specific to a project yeah if you had
some numeric data then you would look at
basic statistics of that data like the
mean the standard deviation you could
look at the proportion of nulls in that
data if that goes up that's a signal
that your data quality has decreased if
you're using Text data then it's less
obvious what you should check but you
could check the length of that text if
something has gone wrong Upstream you
might be getting empty strings coming
through into your pipeline so that's
something you could check and what are
your options if the data fails
validation is that basically signaling
for someone to intervene or is there any
automated step you could take to allow
you to continue you could consider
rerunning the ingestion step if it's
something that's gone wrong in that step
you could change the data that you're
putting into that pipeline but in
general it's a kind of safety valve
against the final model being incorrect
rather than anything that you'd need to
change automatically like that that kind
of raises the question how long is this
whole pipeline going to take I'm sure it
varies drastically
by application but in the systems you've
worked on can you give me idea of the
range of time that the full pipeline
take and the reason I asked that is
because if we're preventing proceeding
with bad data we're saving this amount
of time and so I guess if the whole
thing was very short it wouldn't be a
big deal but if the whole thing was long
then early out could benefit us a lot
the systems I've worked on it's usually
been in the minutes to hours scale so
it's not days and days but the point is
that ideally you would have this
pipeline set up so that it runs
automatically without any interference
from myself without needing to do
anything so it's it's more the being
able to automate it from the start to
the end than particularly the time
saving that's important here I think I
might know the answer to this but does
the data have to be perfect or how can
we judge how tolerant our pipeline is to
bad data I think the the data should be
sort reflective of the real world that
it's trying to model so like if you have
data about your customers about a bunch
of different companies then that's going
to be very variable one thing is that
some machine learning algorithms can't
cope with missing data so in that
situation all the values do need to be
filled out and it needs to be perfect
from that point of view but it can have
a very wide distribution and that's fine
so let me read the next four steps so we
have some idea where this is going and
maybe what to talk about it which Step
so I have next data pre-processing then
model training then model analysis and
validation and then deployment so let's
talk about data pre-processing next I
don't know if this is an official step
or is this depend on the workflow but I
guess how is pre-processing different
from the previous steps pre-processing
is is often synonymous with feature
engineering so that's translating the
raw data into something that you can use
to train the model so if your raw data
was text then it might be word
frequencies or something like that and
that's different from the validation
step because in the validation step
you're describing the data you're
checking that the data doesn't contain
nulls and so on has deep learning kind
of eroded the necessity for feature
engineering I remember I worked on a
project a long time ago and a huge
amount of effort was put into feature
engineering and more recently I worked
on something and they're kind of saying
that feature engineering kind of goes
away in some cases what has your
experience been yeah I think that's
right especially I've worked on a lot of
text models and it's become a lot better
to put to not do much with the text
putting in pretty much raw and have a
more complex model that's able to learn
a lot more from that text rather than
doing extensive feature engineering to
extract those features from the text and
then train the model that seems right to
me okay let's move on to model training
how about this idea of training from
scratch versus fine-tuning an existing
model are both of these possibilities in
a
pipeline I'd say there's actually three
possibilities there's training from
scratch there's fine tuning and there's
retraining the exact same model on new
data training from scratch I wouldn't do
that in my machine learning pipeline I
would do that separately in Standalone
code to get that model established the
first time around check that it is
actually accurate enough to solve that
problem then I would build a machine
learning p line only when I knew that I
had that model and was going to be
retraining it find tuning you can
certainly do within the pipeline because
you might want to tweak the
hyperparameters of that model when
there's new data so you might want to
have a small step within that you
mentioned hyper parameters I was
wondering when you say have the model
and then retrain it what is the model at
that point is it all the parameters
Associated I guess what would be part of
theel model that then gets retrained
what stays yeah that's a great Point
sometimes it's the model architecture
and those hyperparameters and sometimes
it's just the model architecture so if
we're in the neural network world then
the number of layers in that model the
types of layers in there how they're
connected that's probably going to stay
static because changing that up within a
pipeline is hard because you don't don't
have quite such instant feedback on
whether the model is working as you do
in a separate piece of training code
that's just designed to run through
those experiments you've got a lot of
other code around that model that makes
it a little more complex to debug them
you mentioned the duration of the
pipelines you've worked with range from
minutes to hours is most of that time in
the model training yes yeah that's right
usually the other steps are shorter and
it's the model training that's the long
one so that's why it's important to have
those other steps separate so that you
know that your data is in good shape by
the time it gets to the timec consuming
training step another element of time
would be how long we're going to use a
model before retraining how does That
Vary I think very early on I imagine
people used models for a long period of
time and more recently I feel like
people are retraining more and more
often is that a trend yeah I think from
what I've worked on that depends on the
maturity of the use of machine learning
in that organization so early on you
might have built these models fairly ad
hoc and then it's a big effort to deploy
them into production but when you do
that it makes a big step change in the
accuracy of your product whereas as time
goes on you're making smaller
improvements in your product but you
want to make that more frequently so
having that pipeline set up allows you
to change your model often as the input
data changes so yeah I think that's why
you're saying that I guess taking a step
back for a second during all of these
steps of creating a pipeline in what
cases are we able to just hand this over
to software engineers and kind of give
them the information about the model and
in what cases do you feel the data
scientist needs to be involved what's
the trade-off from either a handoff
situation or a collaboration like side
by side
situation part of this is going to
depend on the team that you have and the
skill sets available but I would say
it's very useful to have the data
scientist involved in setting up the
initial pipeline in particular things
like what are the criteria for the data
validation step what is a sensible
distribution of your data what are the
hyperparameters that you should be
considering when you're training the
model and particularly in the step that
we haven't talked about yet which is the
model analysis step I think that's where
the data scientist has a really crucial
part to play I think any data scientist
can learn the skills that they need to
deploy a pipeline but often being able
to debug that complex system being able
to set it up so that it interfaces with
the rest of the product making sure that
it's well tested and so on that's where
a software engineer can add so much
value here I've worked with many
scientists unrelated to data science but
just sort of a you know biologist or
physicist and yeah they can learn to
code as just part of their education are
sort of on the side but then there are
certain skills that they don't have as
much experience in but I definitely feel
that many people end up learning to
program by necessity and I think that's
a good thing for the most part and for
me it's also because I enjoy being able
to write better code it's a lot of fun
being able to do this well and write
code that's robust and scales and so on
you mentioned model analysis and
validation that's the next step so
because the words the same how is this
different from data validation I guess
it's a question of what are we
validating yeah so this is where we're
looking at the performance of the model
in terms of how accurate it is what's
the Precision and recall and also
sometimes splitting that accuracy down
into finer grained sectors so if you had
a model that you were deploying in lots
of different countries does it perform
equally well on the data from all those
countries that's something that you
could do with your validation data which
is the split of your data goes into the
training data and validation or test
data and I know that we're using the
word validation way too many times in
this but that seems to be the way that
the terminology is gone so analysis is
looking at that accuracy across
different aspects this is a point where
you might look for bias in your model as
well is it providing better performance
for certain groups is it providing
better performance on your female users
versus your mail users that would be
something you'd want to look for at this
step and then the validation part of
that is the model should only be
deployed if it is acceptable in all the
analysis criteria so this is kind of
your final go or noo step before you
deploy that model into a production
setting I wanted to flag the term
precision and recall we're not going to
try to go through all that but I'm
guessing that relates to false positives
versus false negatives yes so in a
classification problem that would be
some of the metrics you'd look at and
when you say deciding whether the model
is good enough the reason we might want
to make that decision is maybe we have a
previous model that was pretty good
already and we don't want to make it
worse exactly that's exactly right so
you've taken the same model and
retrained it on new data does it it
perform better as a result of this how
about overfitting versus generalization
I don't know if those are too technical
but can we just give an idea for what
those have to do with the model analysis
this is where if you have overfit your
model then you'll see a higher accuracy
on your training set than on your
validation set and then you'll know that
your model is too closely replicating
your training set and it's not able to
generalize to new data and what you want
it to be able to do is exactly
generalize it to new data when you're
deploying it into production this might
be a naive question but is the size of
the model unrelated to the amount of
training data you have or does the model
size grow depending on the data set if
you have a small data set and a large
model then it's very prone to
overfitting because your model is
basically able to memorize the data that
you have so then it might perform not
that great on when it SE new data yeah
that's a good question and I have this
down as
interpretability I don't know if that's
really part of this step but I guess
that's a element of a model whether you
really understand what it's doing or
whether it's sort of a
blackbox yeah that's definitely part of
model analysis but it's probably not
something that you you might not put
this in the pipeline because for models
where there's like you need to explain
it that's almost the opposite of
automating the problem if you need to
look very carefully into what features
are causing it to make a certain
prediction you can't really do that as
part of an automated setup that's going
to deploy a model as soon as it's
trained you got to take that step back
if you needed to interpret your model
you might run the pipeline up to this
point but then maybe this is where your
data scientist steps in to really take a
good look at that model and then it's a
manual step to deploy it to production
that also kind of raises the point maybe
if we have a large team we're working on
building this Pipeline with the
involvement of data scientists and
software Engineers but then maybe
there's some other data scientists
working on sort of a Next Generation
model or something something like that
so these things could be happening in
parallel it's not like we just drop
everything and build a a static pipeline
that's right yeah so let's start talking
about deployment at this point we have a
pipeline we can run it hopefully with
minimal intervention hopefully it runs
kind of straight through maybe it
retrains with more data what is
different about deployment or maybe
production and I'm sure it varies based
on the project but in general kind of
what is this transition from I have a
pipeline I can run to it's been deployed
which maybe means it's running at a
larger scale or it's running more often
something yeah this is really the point
at which I kind of hand off my tasks to
the software Engineers as well the
pipeline produces a model artifact which
can be a saved set of model weights and
so on and then that's when
model gets handed over and is set up to
run inference so that's really the point
at which the data scientists job is done
that newly trained model has been
produced and now it can be put into the
product so it can provide the service
that it's PL day how does scaling enter
into the equation here is it possible
that our model is too large or too
computationally intensive that we can't
put it in production or is that
something you thought of from very early
on is there sort of a point here where
we have to decide if we can even deploy
this ideally you would know that before
you have started building the pipeline
because a lot of what affects that will
be the model architecture the number of
layers the size of the layers if you're
dealing with a neural network so ideally
you would want to know what some of the
requirements are for inference at the
experimentation stage when you're trying
out lots of models because if you need
your model to be extremely fast you
might limit yourself in those
experiments to models that are small and
fast this might apply to all the steps
not just deployment but what is your
opinion on heavily refactoring and
evolving the initial sort of pipeline
versus rewriting or having a sort of
clean start when you're implementing the
pipeline a lot of the pipeline Solutions
like tense flow extended or Amazon Sage
maker pipelines they will take as inputs
scripts like your training script so you
don't necessarily have to rewrite you
can just kind of pick up the code that
you've used from training and drop that
into the pipeline code that works pretty
well because you already know that
that's working you don't have to
completely rewrite from scratch but a
lot of the
boiler plate around code around the
pipeline is that's new that's coming up
from scratch to actually link those
pieces together and make sure that one
step goes to the next to the next well
one role we didn't talk about at the
start was ml Ops which I guess is an
offshoot of Dev Ops that's more specific
to machine learning do you have any
experience with sort of what could go
wrong in deployment that maybe is
special to machine learning so in
regular backend work there's certain
problems that crop up I'm wondering if
there's any machine learning specific
maybe has to do with monitoring the
inference time or the memory used or
something so one problem that I have
heard about but not experienced myself
is called training and serving skew and
what this is is when you might have
feature engineering code and model
training code and you need to do that
feature engineering when your model is
deployed and running inference as well
as when you're training the model so
what you might do is update that feature
engineering code in your training
Pipeline and then train a model based on
those particular features and then
deploy that model and forget to update
the feature engineering code so when
your model is running inference the data
is coming in it's getting the old
feature engineering but the new model so
the data might be completely valid after
it's had that feature engineering step
the features might be completely valid
but they aren't the right distribution
for that particular model so your model
performs worse and you're not quite sure
why so that's a subtle one that can come
up yes it does sound like very machine
learning specific debugging where yeah
the behavior of this model that we
validated and analyzed is not where we
thought it would be and maybe we have to
roll something back or maybe we're just
we have to fix it so it's good to have
monitoring in production to be able to
sniff out these kinds of things to check
that the model accuracy is what you
expect okay it sounds like we did all
the steps of the pipeline let's start
wrapping up we talked about different
roles throughout this episode do you see
any new roles on the horizon or roles
that you think are changing or becoming
more prominent yeah I think there's a
couple of things here now that I've
started working on generative AI
Solutions AI engineer is the obvious one
someone who's not necessarily building
the model or training the model but is
designing applications that are based on
AI models that's huge and that's only
going to continue to grow as well the
other thing I see is that I think
there's a big place for data scientists
in the world of AI and that's making
sure that that's in evaluating AI models
so if you're trying to use an llm for
some particular business application
it's actually very hard to check how
accurate that model is so I think that's
a huge growth area for data science and
again I think yeah when we say AI
engineer we're talking about people
working with Foundation models of some
type it could be llm or not maybe
they're just working through an API and
they don't run any machine learning
locally at all I guess in some cases
they're programming you know in English
writing prompts and things yeah I think
that's going to be huge in the future
and it already is huge I know we try to
focus on collaboration moving beyond
just the software machine learning what
collaboration me methods have you found
been useful between data scientists and
software Engineers or other members of
the team whether it be a tool or just a
technique that you find is helpful I
think the best way of collaborating is
having a team that's open to ideas it
doesn't speak really to any tools or
techniques it's all about valuing each
other's ideas and the best teams I've
worked on for that have been where
people are very supportive of each other
and supportive of those of someone
bringing in new ideas and that seems to
me to be the key rather than any
particular tool or piece of software so
continuing to wrap up what are you
excited about looking ahead in machine
learning projects you're working on or
that you see in the wider industry so
having relatively recently started
working with llms it just makes me so
just so blown away by the capabilities
at the moment I've been working on a
project to Showcase a good example of a
use of an llm for a startup I'm working
with and the project we decided to
choose was extracting people's flight
details out of an email so you send the
servers an email with your flight
details and it will extract the origin
the destination the time of departure
time of arrival and so on and populate
those into what whatever kind of app you
want to work on and I've worked on
similar projects before and seen things
like big piles of regular expressions or
doing all this complex feature
engineering to get this out of it but
now I can do it in a feline prompt to
open Ai and it works better than all
those previous incredibly complicated
Solutions and you can even do things
like you can ask it for the airport code
instead of the name of the city and even
if the airport code isn't in the email
you can still get that because the LM
has that context so I'm just really
excited about what we're going to be
able to do with these things in the
future yeah I guess that it leads to the
question at the end of a project all the
technical success is there but what is
the business value and sort of what in
the projects you've worked on what are
they doing sort of for the next version
is it usually kind of doubling down on
techniques or is it tackling a
completely new area of the business or
like what are the possible directions at
the end of a project yeah so some of the
projects I've worked on it adds a new
feature that wasn't possible without
machine learning and a lot of these have
been extracting information out of
unstructured data and that gives you the
capability to add something that you
didn't think you were going to be able
to offer some new feature to your
customer and then you know you might
spend some time optimizing that so that
the accuracy improves and so on so I
think yeah it's a balance between
improving these existing models
improving the accuracy and then the step
change of adding a completely new
feature okay where can listeners find
out more about you or your new book best
place is to follow me on LinkedIn okay I
will put your handle or your LinkedIn
name in the show notes thanks for
talking to me today Catherine thanks
will it's been great talking to you this
is Philip Winston for software
engineering radio thanks for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at
[Music]
sr.ntr or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
commments license
2.5 thanks for listening